<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog</id>
    <title>Story of God Blog</title>
    <updated>2023-12-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Story of God Blog</subtitle>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deuteronomy 30-31 & Psalm 63]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-30-31</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-30-31"/>
        <updated>2023-12-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A thought on 30 It feels related to 2912 “It is not in the heavens... nor beyond the sea... but the word is very near you, in your mouth and in your heart that you. may follow it”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A thought on 30:11 (“not too difficult nor far away”): It feels related to 29:29 “The secret things belong to the Lord our God, but the things revealed belong to us, and to our sons forever, so that we may follow all the words of this Torah” and 30:12 “It is not in the heavens... nor beyond the sea... but the word is very near you, in your mouth and in your heart that you. may follow it”</p><p>I think there is a subtlety to the Torah, us failing it, and Jesus fulfilling it. Genesis indicates that our human vocation is to be the Lord’s partners on earth, and his covenants like this are not inscrutable or undoable (the plain reading of 30:11). Yet we humans didn’t fulfill them, Jesus did, we still don’t, yet we still must (Matt 5:20) by his power and example (Phil 2:5). Somehow these are all true, even if they rub against our various traditions’ systems of interpretation of human nature and how God “logically” must work.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deuteronomy 28-39 & Psalm 62]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-28-39</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-28-39"/>
        <updated>2023-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[29 "The secret things belong to the Lord our God, but the things revealed belong to us and to our sons forever, so that we may follow all the words of this Law."]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>29:29: "The secret things belong to the Lord our God, but the things revealed belong to us and to our sons forever, so that we may follow all the words of this Law."</p><p>I could do a lot more thinking about this.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deuteronomy 24-27 & Psalm 61]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-24-27</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-24-27"/>
        <updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many of these recent laws feel like they are answering Cain’s question from Gen 4: "Am I my brother’s keeper?"]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many of these recent laws feel like they are answering Cain’s question from Gen 4: "Am I my brother’s keeper?"</p><p>I wonder if this was some of the seed of imagination in Jesus responding to "Who is my neighbor?"</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deuteronomy 17-20 & Psalm 59]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-17-20</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-17-20"/>
        <updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The list of restrictions (17]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The list of restrictions (17:16) for future kings is interesting:</p><ol><li>Don’t acquire lots of horses</li><li>Don’t make people return to Egypt to get horses</li><li>Don’t acquire many wives</li><li>Don’t greatly increase in gold/silver</li></ol><p>Solomon will break all 4 of these.</p><p>Also (17:18) a king is supposed to make their own copy of the Torah to keep and read daily to keep him humble. Imagine if political leaders read scripture with an eye toward staying humble and not enriching themselves 😬</p><p>18:15 an Israelite prophet like Moses is coming. Who will it be? “To him you shall listen.” Remember what the voice from the cloud said at the Transfiguration.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deuteronomy 4-6 & Psalm 54]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-4-6</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/deuteronomy-4-6"/>
        <updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Moses seems to be saying the Lord gave the nations the heavenly hosts? (429-31 saying the time for that is over with Jesus?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Moses seems to be saying the Lord gave the nations the heavenly hosts? (4:19) Is Paul working with this worldview in Acts 17:29-31 saying the time for that is over with Jesus?</p><p>In 5:3-4 is the emphasis of “did not make this covenant with our fathers, but with us” on the distinction between the people of the Exodus and the patriarchs?</p><p>5:11 Now that I’ve heard Dr. Carmen Imes explain “bearing” the Lord’s name, the translation “take the name... in vain” seems so impoverished.</p><p>Ps 54:4 God is my “helper” is the same word in Gen 2:18 “helper corresponding to <!-- -->[the man]<!-- -->”
Also Dr Imes: this kind of helper is “not someone to make you sandwiches” 😂</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 35-36 & Psalm 52]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-35-36</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-35-36"/>
        <updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[One interesting thing is the first mention of the cities of refuge for non-premeditated or possibly accidental killers. Numbers 35:24 “then the congregation shall judge between the one who fatally struck the victim and the blood avenger”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One interesting thing is the first mention of the cities of refuge for non-premeditated or possibly accidental killers. Numbers 35:24 “then the congregation shall judge between the one who fatally struck the victim and the blood avenger”</p><p>We take for granted that even murderers get trials, with presumed innocence until proven guilty. But that’s the gift of a legal tradition we’ve inherited. Many ancient cultures assumed vigilante justice, but here a big limit gets put on it.</p><p>It also echoes what comes after the first murder in Genesis, when the Lord sets a sign for Cain “so that no one finding him would kill him.” The refuge cities function like Cain’s sign.</p><p>Another parallel with Genesis 4:
“you are cursed from the ground which has opened its mouth to receive your brother’s blood from your hand.” And Numbers “blood defiles the land... So you shall not defile the land in which you live, in the midst of which I dwell.”</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 25-27 & Psalm 48]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-25-27</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-25-27"/>
        <updated>2023-11-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Num 27 “‘...so that the congregation of the Lord will not be like sheep that have no shepherd.’ So the Lord said to Moses, ‘Take Ye(ho)shua... a man in whom is the Spirit...’”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Num 27:17-18: “‘...so that the congregation of the Lord will not be like sheep that have no shepherd.’ So the Lord said to Moses, ‘Take Ye(ho)shua... a man in whom is the Spirit...’”</p><p>Matt 9:36: “When <!-- -->[Yeshua]<!-- --> saw the crowds, he had compassion on them, because they were harassed and helpless, like sheep without a shepherd.”</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 22-24 & Psalm 47]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-22-24</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-22-24"/>
        <updated>2023-11-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I love the Balaam story. It’s so complex. Somehow he knows about and speaks to Yahweh, yet is not his friend (nor is Yahweh his friend... this is the first time in the story the Hebrew word “satan”—adversary, never a proper name—shows up with Yahweh setting himself as Balaam’s adversary).]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love the Balaam story. It’s so complex. Somehow he knows about and speaks to Yahweh, yet is not his friend (nor is Yahweh his friend... this is the first time in the story the Hebrew word “satan”—adversary, never a proper name—shows up with Yahweh setting himself as Balaam’s adversary).
Fascinating what Balaam is known for by Balak: “he whom you bless is blessed, and he whom you curse is cursed.”—and dark twist on the Lord’s blessing to Abraham and his descendants.
Everyone in this episode is involved in attempting dark mystical death-dealing, but it just crescendoes to blessings on Israel and prophecy of a future (“not near” / “not now”) king from Israel, despite all this.</p><p>I don’t know about the meaning here, but Num 24:1-2 is interesting: “When Balaam saw that it pleased the Lord to bless Israel, he did not go as at other times to seek omens, rather he turned his face toward the wilderness. And Balaam raised his eyes and saw Israel... and the Spirit of God came upon him.”
I don’t know about this, but on this third time where one opposed to the Lord has death-dealing words turned to life, he turns to the wilderness, with the Spirit of God, and points to the Messiah, echoing the blessing to Abraham, as we’re nearing Deuteronomy.
Jesus, after being baptized, was led by the Spirit, into the wilderness, to meet his adversary, who tries to deal death with cursed words, which Jesus rebuts 3 times with words from Deuteronomy. 🤯</p><p>It's also funny that Balaam gives three literall ass-beatings 🫏</p><p>RE: “ascended” in Ps 47:5, this is likely not ancient ignorance of not knowing the Lord is everywhere and not confined to certain places. Biblical positional language about ascending and descending is not a 2 or 3D literal thing. Similarly, geography isn’t always either (Ps 48:2 Zion isn’t literally in the far north, but it is in terms of cosmic significance... but that’s a whole rabbit trail about digs at Baal). Ancient chief gods were said to ascend and ride clouds and such, so Biblical language to that effect for the Lord signifies in a way that makes cultural sense that, yes, he has all the power and glory, but pay attention to all the ways that the Lord is quite distinct from the gods, now that we’ve got your attention with this deity symbolism you Ancient Near Easterners know all about.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 19-21 & Psalm 46]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-19-21</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-19-21"/>
        <updated>2023-11-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting bit: the fiery snakes/bronze snake are the first appearance of the word “seraphim” in the Bible.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Interesting bit: the fiery snakes/bronze snake are the first appearance of the word “seraphim” in the Bible.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 14-16 & Psalm 44]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-14-16</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-14-16"/>
        <updated>2023-11-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ordering of commands and narrative today messed with me. I was enjoying the bit about the violet thread at the corner of the Israelites’ clothes as a reminder to see with the eyes of heaven as they went about their day-to-day. A little thread of tabernacle for every member of the kingdom of priests. Anachronistically, this feels a bit “democratic”. Probably a lot more beauty for me to think about there...]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The ordering of commands and narrative today messed with me. I was enjoying the bit about the violet thread at the corner of the Israelites’ clothes as a reminder to see with the eyes of heaven as they went about their day-to-day. A little thread of tabernacle for every member of the kingdom of priests. Anachronistically, this feels a bit “democratic”. Probably a lot more beauty for me to think about there...</p><p>But then comes the rebellion of some of the Levites, and it feels like they are using this symbolism with the violet threads that brings a bit of tabernacle to everyone, to cause trouble. Do they feel threatened that everyone gets some purple thread when the Levites were supposed to be special? Are they jealous of the priesthood and Aaron and Moses, a subset of the Levites (that seems to be what they are saying more directly)? Whatever it was, they are clearly not happy with their place in the ordering of the nation, and it seems like the symbolism of the violet threads for everyone set them off.</p><p>Whatever happened with the judgment of the sons of Korah, some must have survived, since many of the Psalms are attributed to the sons of Korah.</p><p>RE: “third and fourth” generations. Literally in Hebrew, it’s “to the third and fourth” (“generation” implied, but not there literally). “3...4” is a Hebrew turn of phrase, something like “a few” or “as much as needed” and shows up even in poetic couplets like Proverbs 30:18.</p><p>The handful of generations should be compared to the “thousands of generations of those who love me and keep my commandments” who receive the Lord’s steadfast love (gracious, compassionate, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love). Sometimes people repeat their parents’ mistakes/rebellions for a few generations, but the Lord’s steadfast love is orders of magnitude greater than the effects of those.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numbers 8-10 & Psalm 42]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-8-10</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/numbers-8-10"/>
        <updated>2023-11-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Psalm 42 “Who can we go to? You have the words of everlasting life.”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Psalm 42:1-2 reminds me of Peter saying to Jesus: “Who can we go to? You have the words of everlasting life.”</p><p>V3 probably refers to human enemies or “the nations.” This question, “Where is your God?”comes from those two subjects in a handful of other places in the Hebrew Bible, but in v3, the word “they” isn’t even in the Hebrew.</p><p>The last verse is beautiful:</p><p>Why are you in despair, my soul?
And why are you restless within me?
Wait for God, for I will again praise Him
For the “yeshua” of His presence, my God.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exodus 10-12 & Psalm 20]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-10-12</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-10-12"/>
        <updated>2023-10-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Regarding the exclusion of foreigners from Passover, a couple ideas...]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Regarding the exclusion of foreigners from Passover, a couple ideas...</p><ol><li><p>It notes that a foreigner can be circumcised with his household and then “come near” (temple language) and observe Passover.</p></li><li><p>Passover marks the beginning of the new calendar before they head to Sinai and enter the covenant. That covenant begins with ten “commandments” (literally “ten words”), the first of which is “I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery.” Passover is the divine rescue that is the basis for the covenant, so only participants in the covenant can observe it.</p></li></ol><p>There is a case to be made that Jesus gave Communion as a Passover parallel (he called this ritual meal a new covenant, and the timing...), Paul treats it seriously, and we rightly give it reverence. It’s open to all, but only after joining that covenant, same as for Passover.</p><p>Lev 10:10 to Aaron (priests) “You are to distinguish between the holy and the common.” Practicing distinction is essential to priesthood. Radically, Israel is also to be a kingdom of priests, and even more radically, apparently foreigners can join, if they take the terms of the covenant.</p><p>Just as the Passover was an unconditioned gift to redeem Israel that led to a covenant with conditions (but open to all who will accept them), Jesus’s sacrifice is an unconditioned gift that leads us to a new covenant, open to all who will accept the terms of his new covenant.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exodus 4-6 & Psalm 18]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-4-6</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-4-6"/>
        <updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Moses brings up his speech problems twice.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Moses brings up his speech problems twice.</p><p>Interesting thing pointed out to me recently: Zipporah is the last of 7 women at the beginning of Exodus that save Moses, the Exodus, and the covenant: Shiphrah, Puah (midwives), Moses’ mom and sister (put him in the Nile), Pharaoh’s daughter and servant (draw him out), and Zipporah.
I think the narrator gives us the truncated genealogy to root the priesthood in the tribe of Levi, but not sure why Reuben and Simeon get mentioned first, except that these are the first 3 sons of Jacob in birth order.</p><p>The Lord to Moses: “Go back to Egypt, for all the men who were seeking your life are dead.”</p><p>In Matthew 2 an angel tells Joseph to go back “to the land of Israel, for those who sought the child’s life are dead.” Matthew with some harsh criticism for how Egypt-like Israel had become. I’m constantly amazed at how realistic the Hebrew scriptural tradition is, pointing out their society’s own failings.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exodus 1-3 & Psalm 17]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-1-3</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/exodus-1-3"/>
        <updated>2023-10-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[So many Genesis bits showing up in the beginning of Exodus.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So many Genesis bits showing up in the beginning of Exodus.</p><ul><li>The sons of Israel being fruitful and multiplying and “swarming” (Gen 1).</li><li>Come let us deal shrewdly (🐍)</li><li>Mortar and bricks (tower in Babylon)</li><li>Moses in the “basket” same word as the “ark”of the flood and pitched with pitch to rescue from the water of death.</li></ul><p>Deuteronomy 4:12 (Then the Lord spoke to you from the midst of the fire; you heard the sound of words, but you saw no form—there was only a voice)
This fire is the one the people saw at the mountain. But apparently Moses saw some kind of human form in the burning bush (?), since “the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a blazing fire from the midst of the bush” in other words, he saw the angel inside the bush, which blew my mind, since most depictions (Prince of Egypt, Ten Commandments movie, drawings) don’t show this.</p><p>In my looking so far, the angel of Yahweh (maybe all angels?) has either had a human form described, or else no visual description, but I don’t know for sure. I certainly had always pictured the bush like in the movies, but then started to wonder when thinking about the 4th man in the fire that did not burn up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and then it felt almost scandalous comprehending the episode in Exodus 24 when the seventy elders of Israel go up the mountain with Moses, Aaron, and his sons, and “they saw the God of Israel; and under his feet like a pavement of sapphire... Yet he did not reach out his hand against the nobles... and they saw God, and they ate and drank.” It felt... wrong... for them to see God with feet and hands, but I had to assume my conceptions were just wrong, maybe even the burning bush movie version.</p><p>We certainly get a multifaceted view of God in the Bible, who is unchanging yet constantly surprising and uncontainable... “Will God indeed dwell on the earth? Behold, the heavens and the heaven of heavens cannot contain you...” (1 Kings 8:27)</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 48-50 & Psalm 16]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-48-50</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-48-50"/>
        <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've always loved "you meant evil for me, but God meant it for good in order... to keep many people alive." God used what people meant for evil to make known through Joseph the way of life through the famine. Profound in the story, with a cosmic ring to it.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've always loved "you meant evil for me, but God meant it for good in order... to keep many people alive." God used what people meant for evil to make known through Joseph the way of life through the famine. Profound in the story, with a cosmic ring to it.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 46-47 & Psalm 15]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-46-47</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-46-47"/>
        <updated>2023-10-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[70 people from the house of Jacob (numbering the men) come to Egypt who will become a new nation out of the 70 nations divided at Babylon.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>70 people from the house of Jacob (numbering the men) come to Egypt who will become a new nation out of the 70 nations divided at Babylon.</p><p>It "rhymes" with Deuteronomy 32:8-9:</p><blockquote><p>When the Most High gave the nations their inheritance,<br>
When he separated the sons of adam,<br>
He set the boundaries of the peoples<br>
According to the number of the sons of elohim.<br>
For Yahweh's portion is his people;<br>
Jacob is the allotment of his inheritance."</p></blockquote><p>Note: Some translations <a href="https://www.logos.com/grow/sons-of-israel-or-sons-of-god-in-deuteronomy-32-8-9/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">incorrectly</a> say "according to the number of the sons of Israel."</p><p>The table of 70 nations after the tower of Babylon is followed by Yahweh calling Abram out as the start of a new nation. Now, his descendants are nominally 70 as the response to human (sons of adam) and divine (sons of elohim) rebellion and division, and the vehicle of future blessing of all those nations (Genesis 12:3), but not the sons of elohim (Psalm 82 6-8):</p><blockquote><p>In you all the families of the ground (adamah) will be be blessed</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>I said, you are gods,<br>
And all of you are sons of the Most High.<br>
Nevertheless you will die like men (adam),<br>
And fall (niphalu, a verb form of nephilim) like one of the princes.<br>
Arise, elohim, judge the land!<br>
For you possess all the nations.</p></blockquote><p>70 people is small next to 70 nations. Maybe this is part of why, along with Isaiah's suffering servant and of course Jesus being "lifted up" as king by being put on a cross of shame, it's natural for Paul to say:</p><blockquote><p>God has chosen the weak things of the world to shame the things which are strong, and the insignificant things of the world and the despised God has chosen.</p></blockquote><p>With Psalm 15 in mind, this is more than a mere Cinderella story; these chosen will have a weighty responsibility to be able to "settle on Yahweh's holy hill."</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 32-34 & Psalm 12]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-38-40</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-38-40"/>
        <updated>2023-10-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Judah/Er/Onan/Tamar story is definitely strange, and I've heard colorful conclusions about the story's meaning jumped to in the past.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Judah/Er/Onan/Tamar story is definitely strange, and I've heard colorful conclusions about the story's meaning jumped to in the past.</p><p>This time I tried to pay attention to repetition to see if anything popped. NASB gives some help about where English translation is sometimes smoothing over repeated words.</p><ol><li>Judah "went down" from his brothers to find his wife</li><li>Er, Judah's firstborn "was evil in the sight of Yahweh, so Yahweh took his life."
No explanation about what he did that was evil.</li><li>Judah tells #2 Onan to perform his duty to "raise up a seed" for his brother.
This is the command in Deuteronomy 25:5-10; if not followed, the widow was to spit in his face and publicly shame the brother.</li><li>Onan knew that "the seed would not be his" so he spilled "on the ground" so that he would not "give a seed" to his brother.</li><li>This was "evil in the sight of Yahweh, so he took his life also."</li><li>Judah doesn't honor what would be codified in Deuteronomy 25:5 for #3 Shelah and eventually
Tamar seems to be vindicated.</li></ol><p>"Went down" / "on the ground" contrasts with "raise up a seed." Er, Onan, and Judah all fail with increasing details given, and Tamar gets a strange honor at the end. Given Judah's role in the messianic line and the focus on "the seed" it feels like the plot conflict is that the seed (tying back to Genesis 3:15) is not going to be "raised up" due to the moral failure of 3 men, so a woman steps in and makes it happen. Was that the "right" thing to do? The narrator doesn't tell us, and leaves us scratching our heads about the perversions, but the plot conflict gets resolved, and their son Perez ends up an ancestor of the Lion of the tribe of Judah.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 32-34 & Psalm 10]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-32-34</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-32-34"/>
        <updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Translation hides the fact that "angel" is just the word "messenger."]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Translation hides the fact that "angel" is just the word "messenger."
Messengers of God meet Jacob, and Jacob sends messengers to Esau. God
meeting Jacob will parallel Jacob meeting Esau.</p><p>It struck me that Jacob's plans to send gifts ahead to Esau ("And behold,
<!-- -->[Jacob]<!-- --> also is behind us") the day before he meets him is with the
reasoning in fear: "Then afterward I will see his <em>face</em>; perhaps he will accept
me." But then, following the wrestling with God, he says "I have seen God <em>face</em>
to <em>face</em>, yet my life has been spared."
("But he himself passed on ahead of them") on his way to his brother. Even
though he sends his family in reverse order of his own favoritism, he puts
himself last by going first, maybe with some new boldness that if he can see God
face to face and be spared, maybe he can see Esau's face and be spared.</p><p>That resonates with some deep need for wildness. I'd rather have God hold my
shoulders and give a firm shake to get my attention than to be gently ignored.</p><p>The episodes of preparing to meet and actually meeting Esau is separated by
wrestling with God. You can feel the suspense as he's by himself awaiting the
reckoning with his past, which is when God shows up to Jacob. To me it felt
like a constrast with Abraham's two covenant encounters with God (15 &amp; 17)
separated by disastrous mistreatment of Hagar (16) who herself gets a visit from
the messenger of Yahweh.</p><p>In other random thoughts, I've long held that America is not a "Christian
nation" because it confuses worldly power for the self-giving way of Jesus. And
I do think it's vital not to read America into the Bible, or ancient Israel,
and certainly not the church.</p><p>But today I wondered, with the confusion about who we are as a country, whether
there is a place for envisioning America hopefully as patterned in its
architecture after a Judeo-Christian Exodus structure whose pluralism is
inherent in that patterning itself.</p><ol><li>Judaic: Founded on laws that order society for a common good and protect
the quartet of the vulnerable: widows, orphans, foreigners, &amp; the poor.</li><li>Christian: Founded on a belief in a new way to be human (where real power
is in serving) and pluralist because that new way to be human speaks for
itself without coercion.</li><li>A nation of Exodus: Simultaneously a people set free, a refuge for those
seeking liberty, and a body infected with injustice in need of constant
reform.</li></ol>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 16-18 & Psalm 5]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-16-18</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-16-18"/>
        <updated>2023-10-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Of the slaves Abram acquired in Egypt as a result of mistreating his wife, is]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Of the slaves Abram acquired in Egypt as a result of mistreating his wife, is
Hagar (the stranger / the immigrant). She "took" and "gave" her "to her husband"
(Genesis 3). Hagar starts to feel superior to Sarai. Abram "solves" this by saying
"your" slave woman is "in your hand. Do to her what is good in your eyes." This
results in Sarai abusing Hagar.</p><p>Right after this, Yahweh appears to Abram, saying "walk before me and be blameless"
which is not what he had just done. But God establishes an everlasting covenant.
The sign of this covenant is a sensitive one for all the males, in the area they
make life, after Abram and Sarai had taken advantage of a woman in a vulnerable life
situation.</p><p>When the 3 men / Yahweh appear to Abraham, and Abraham intercedes for Sodom, he appeals
to Yahweh as the "judge of all the land" who should do justice. Even as Abraham fears
overstepping his bounds, Yahweh concedes every grace Abraham asks for. There is no
bargaining happening. But Yahweh hears the outcry from Sodom and Gomorrah and will
act on behalf of those crying out.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 12-15 & Psalm 4]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-12-15</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-12-15"/>
        <updated>2023-10-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The means of blessing to all the earth's families is revealed through a specific]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The means of blessing to all the earth's families is revealed through a specific
call to obedience by Abram, and he obeys, kind of. "Go from your country and
from your relatives..." "and Lot went with him."</p><p>Then Abram goes to Egypt and gets wealth and life at the expense of Sarai ("that
I may live on account of you") rather than getting life via trust in the Lord
(Genesis 3 again, even with Sarai: saw-beautiful-took).</p><p>Abram's lack of trust means Yahweh even has to bring harm to Pharaoh who seems
innocent here, for the sake of his promise to Abram.</p><p>But Abram does a repeat and "called on the name of Yahweh" at the same spot as
before Egypt, but actions from lack of trust will still cause him problems:</p><ul><li>Lot: strife between herdsmen</li><li>"gifts" from Pharaoh that make Abram wealthy, including female servants,
including Hagar, whom Abram and Sarai will later abuse. He later refuses
gifts from the king of Salem so he can't say "I've made Abram rich." Maybe
this is a repentance from letting the king of Egypt do that to him.</li><li>Lot: Abram has to rescue after the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fall into tar
pits (grim foreshadowing)</li></ul><p>Psalm 4: "In peace I will both lie down and sleep, for you alone, Lord, have me
dwell in safety." Something for me to meditate on when my mind races at night.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 8-11 & Psalm 3]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-8-11</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-8-11"/>
        <updated>2023-10-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Names are apparently very important in Genesis 1-11:]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Names are apparently very important in Genesis 1-11:</p><ul><li>The human has the job of naming the animals</li><li>The human names his wife</li><li>Cain names the first city after his son.</li><li>Parents name their children</li><li>The Nephilim (translated "fallen ones") are all about being strong and having a great name.</li><li>Noah's son Shem (translated "Name") is an ancestor of Abram</li><li>The builders of Babylon are all about making a name for themselves, but end up with a confused name.</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 4-7 & Psalm 2]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-4-7</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-4-7"/>
        <updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today's video succinctly summarizes the pattern of seeing something good]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today's video succinctly summarizes the pattern of seeing something good
and taking, and its results. It's hard to not see now, like
with the rebellion of the spiritual beings in Genesis 6: they "saw" that the
daughters of humanity were "good" and "took" resulting in mighty men who
make their own name great and cause problems later in the promised land.</p><p>The part that keeps pulling on my heart, though, is from Genesis 4.
Yes, I am my brother's keeper. It's a natural extension of the Genesis 1-2
ideal. And Psalm 2 adds a cosmic scope to it: the nations and the ends of the
earth in the kingdom of the Lord's messiah.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genesis 1-3 & Psalm 1]]></title>
        <id>https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-1-3</id>
        <link href="https://my-site.com/journal/blog/genesis-1-3"/>
        <updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've spent a lot of time in the last few years learning about the ancient context]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've spent a lot of time in the last few years learning about the ancient context
of the Hebrew Bible, and the ancient Near East worldview of the three-tiered
cosmos. It's now hard to not see it in Genesis 1 now. I've also learned maybe fifty Hebrew words and benefited from <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ppkdrGStHxm9Q1sjj7qZwf3yqNkwGVU9sumD9LMMTPU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">un-translating</a> select words from Genesis
1-11.</p><p>What jumps out at me now is about the serpent (nachash) and the tree of knowing
good and bad. The nachash doesn't strictly utter any false propositions:</p><ol><li>"Did elohim actually say, 'You shall not eat of any tree in the garden'?"
It's just a question, not a statement.</li><li>"You will not surely die."
She didn't die. No mention of consequences.</li><li>"For elohim knows that in the day you eat of it your eyes will be opened, and
you will be like elohim, knowing good and bad."
She is already like elohim (Genesis 1), and she would "know" good and bad,
<em>experientially</em></li></ol><p>The nachash lies while uttering no technically false statements.
The nachash even uses language from Yahweh's command that Eve does not quote:</p><ol><li><em>surely</em> die</li><li><em>in the day</em> you eat of it</li></ol><p>The nachash never utters Yahweh's name, but always uses "elohim."</p><p>Eve <em>saw</em> that the tree was:</p><ol><li>Good for food</li><li>A delight to the eyes</li><li>Desirable for wisdom</li></ol><p>And she <em>took</em></p><p>Wisdom <em>is</em> desirable and surely Yahweh wanted the humans to have it, so that
they could rule properly as his images. How were they intended to get it?
In the language of the narrative, maybe the tree of knowing good and bad <em>was</em>
the means of acquiring wisdom to judge between good and bad, but the proper way
to acquire it was to obey and not eat of it.
Was the tree guaranteed to give knowledge of good and bad one way or another?
Either through experience by eating of it in disobedience,
or through wisdom by obeying in trust? "The fear of Yahweh is the beginning of
wisdom" according to Psalms and Proverbs. Apparently the right way to "know"
good and bad is a process that starts with trusting and obeying Yahweh, whereas
seeing and taking can cause "knowing" it experientially, and painfully quickly.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Adam Liechty</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/adamliechty</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="journal" term="journal"/>
    </entry>
</feed>